RICHARD CRIPPEN

Atlanta, GA 30317

https://github.com/rickyonthephone| Portfolio: Write out Link

SUMMARY

I am a full stack web developer with a 20-year career history working in client services in the financial services industry. I am known for my creativity, tenacity, and willingness to be a "student of the industry" as to stay abreast of the latest news and how it affects both my career as well as projects I work on for my clientele.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Languages: HTML, CSS, JavaScript/jQuery, SQL

Applications: Bootstrap, Visual Studio Code, GitHub, node.js, APIs, MS Office Suite,

Camtasia, Tableau

PROJECTS

Home Kitchen Pro | rickyonthephone.github.io/project1repo

- First bootcamp project creating an app to pull meal and cocktail recipes along with wine parings,
- Acted as Project Manager to ensure timely deliverables and primarily worked on the overall concept design, wireframing, API research, and HTML code.
- Project app was created using JavaScript, HTML, CSS, and two third party APIs.

Weather Dashboard | rickyonthephone.github.io/Weather Dashboard/

- Weather Dashboard project to relay current weather along with a 5-day weather forecast for a selected city.
- This dashboard was created by me as an exercise to practice various skills in programming languages.
- The weather application was created using JavaScript, HTML, CSS, and a third-party API. Sought to exercise utilization of compiled JavaScript knowledge using local storage, for loops, DOM manipulation, and event listeners as well as practice organizing HTML/CSS structures and apply responsive design.

Workday Planner | rickyonthephone.github.io/Work Day Scheduler/

- Workday Planner project was created to annotate daily tasks to stay organized.
- This application was created by me as an exercise to practice various skills in programming languages and familiarize myself using iQuery syntax.
- The application was created using JavaScript/jQuery, HTML, and CSS. The primary goals sought were to exercise utilization jQuery syntax, use local storage, use moment.js, DOM manipulation, and use event listeners.

Password Generator | rickyonthephone.github.io/JavaScript Password Generator/

- Password generator designed to create random password based on user criteria.
- This project was created by me to exercise newly learned JavaScript programming.
- The password generator was created using JavaScript, HTML, and CSS.

EXPERIENCE

Communications Consultant/Engagement Strategist Voya Financial

2017 – 2020 Atlanta, GA

Acted as the primary consultant for communications and marketing solutions for retirement benefits. Managed a book of business comprised of 12 Fortune 500 companies with plan assets greater than \$500 M. Primarily worked on projects requiring digital solutions to communicate with company employees and frequently integrated with third parties to construct microsites, create eBooks, design custom emails and landing pages.

Key Accomplishments:

- Standardized a communications approach for clients with heavy M & A activity to communicate to affected employees (either incoming or outgoing) on timelines for asset transfers, investment mapping, and deliver necessary DOL legal notices.
- Received a book of business that was largely neglected by a predecessor and worked to make my role and offered services more prominent in each of my clients' organizations.
 Between 2017 and 2020 I had gotten all of my clients to utilize our communications and marketing services.
- Took on communications and marketing efforts to support Voya's entry into the nonqualified retirement plan market for my clients who offered non-qualified plans to their employees.
- Analyzed clienteles' retirement plan participants to gain insights into participant behaviors, media preferences, demographics, and psychographics in order to partner internally to incorporate behavioral finance and segmentation research for future strategic initiatives.
- Wrote and designed creative briefs leveraging industry insights along with client data to provide new ideas and/or inspiration for strategic projects and then funnel those results into actionable projects.
- Built relationships across clients' organization spanning from day-to-day HR/Payroll/Benefits contacts up to senior level executives.

Deferred Compensation Administrator Employees' Retirement System of Georgia

2011 – 2017 Atlanta, GA

Worked in a multi-dimensional role that mainly fell into three different parts: assist with the day-to-day administration of the State of Georgia Employees' 401(k) and 457 deferred compensation plans (commonly referred to as Peach State Reserves), supported employee outreach for benefit education on the defined benefit (i.e., pension) plan, and worked to create, edit, and review plan all retirement plan communications.

Key Accomplishments:

- Won the 2013 Excellence in HR award from Council of State Personnel Administrator (a multi-agency organization comprised of HR and Benefits professionals for "consistently providing information and assistance as needed in a manner that is courteous and easy to understand. His unique approach has been quite helpful as a partner of the HR community in helping us better serve our employees' concerns regarding financial and retirement futures."
- Conducted both employee and employer training on deferred compensation and defined benefit plan topics.

- Began writing SQL queries to troubleshoot inconsistent data which inevitably comes when you have HR and Payroll departments that are de-centralized
- Continued with the State of Georgia's new iteration of retirement benefits for the newest employees which implemented a 401(k) match and a new pension plan calculation.

Institutional Plan Service Sales Manager ING

2006 - 2011 Atlanta, GA

Managed a team of 4 plan consultants who were dedicated to servicing the State of Georgia's 401(k) and 457 deferred compensation retirement programs.

Key Accomplishments:

- Consistently met all office productivity goals for rollovers, enrollments, and onsite education meetings.
- Took over communications and education programs for the State of Georgia pension benefit (this benefit was previously out-of-scope for the contract negotiated between ING and Georgia)
- Built valuable relationships with senior level officials at many agencies and in all three branches of state government. These relationships were key to get "buy in" to go onsite and meet with employees.

Workforce Analyst & Retirement Services Associate Invesco

2000 - 2006 Atlanta, GA

Began my career at Invesco as a bilingual inbound call center Retirement Services Associate fielding clienteles' employees' calls regarding their retirement benefits. I was promoted to the Workforce Analyst position in the call center in 2005 which forecast call volumes, anticipated head count needed to meet service agreements, and assisted with the management of many of the day-to-day operations of the call center.

EDUCATION, AWARDS & LICENSES

Bootcamp Certificate: Georgia Tech University, Atlanta, GA

A 24-week intensive program focused on gaining technical programming skills in HTML5, CSS3, JavaScript, jQuery, Bootstrap, Firebase, Node Js, MySQL, MongoDB, Express, Handelbars.js & ReactJS. Program summary available upon request.

Degree: Bachelor of Arts in Economics Appalachian State University, Boone, NC

Scholastic Awards: Winner of the 1999 ASU Brashear Prize for excellence in economic research and writing. Topic I wrote on was behavioral economics and intrinsic value of environmental resources.

Former licensures: From 2000 until 2014 I held Series 6, 7, 63, and 65 licenses through FINRA (Financial Industry Regulatory Authority, which was previously referred to as the NASD – National Association of Securities Dealers) for securities and mutual fund sales practices. During that time I kept a clean form U4 with no reported violations regarding my career.

Languages: Formerly fluent in Spanish, no longer fluent but I can still converse on an above average level.